This factory initially produced all kinds of
and sizes of paper, for shop counters,
to make cone bags, from that old-fashioned paper.
Nowadays, it mainly focuses on packaging paper.
When the factory was founded,
the width of this machine was
ninety-centimetres,
that was the width of that ‘calandra’.
Then my father's predecessors
widened it to one metre twenty.
And we, about 40 years ago,
widened it again to two metres thirty.
Because of wages,
and to remain competitive,
and also because of paper sizes,
that's why it was made wider.
That was around...
he bought it around...
in ‘41, bought it then, and started
operating it in ‘43.
This is a system that was used about a hundred years
ago.
Here in the paper department, where we are talking about,
seven, seven workers worked,
but in the past,
it wasn't ours yet,
but I knew it, I remember,
they worked,
they didn't work in the summer.
There was no power source, so they didn't work.
Later, wages had to continue to be paid,
and with the advent of ‘motorisation’ ,
those two things came together
and then work continued throughout the year,
in summer and winter.
In the beginning, it didn't have millstones in that form,
later my father built the millstones into it.
You put the paper in there to recycle it,
the old paper
together with water.
This is an industry that comes to a standstill immediately
if the water stops flowing in here,
just like when the power goes out,
the power goes out, it's exactly the same.
Then it stays like that for a few hours,
about two hours, to dissolve.
Then it goes to a ‘refining machine’,
a cylinder or a kind of ‘refiner’.
It goes into that cylinder,
and stays there for about twenty minutes,
or half an hour,
depending on what is needed,
to refine the pulp.
Then it goes into the vat,
where it is transported further.
This is done by a wheel called the ‘Maxão’ wheel.
Nowadays, there are pumps
that can do that.
Then it goes with the water over the plates,
it flows with the water over the plates.
The pulp and the water...
you can't see whether there is paper in it or not.
Then it goes into a drum
with a cylinder inside that rotates,
and it's closed.
It has a pump that sucks the water out,
so that it is always dry on the inside,
that drum that is cylindrical, and the paper
separates from the water.
And that's how the paper is formed,
over and over again.
That motor is the most important part.
If it stops,
that causes the water to be sucked in.
And that creates pressure
which makes the paper stick to the roll.
And then, where the paper sticks
to it, is wool.
And the paper, the pulp, sticks to the wool,
and leaves the roll,
that roll is made of metal,
of copper,
and then it comes onto this ‘calandra’,
and we tension it.
It has a wooden clamp underneath,
with rubber on the outside,
and above that it is made of iron.
And we have to stretch it,
to make the paper as dry as possible,
otherwise the paper breaks,
it becomes a pile of wet paper
that cannot be transported.
We have to stretch it on both sides
to squeeze out as much water as possible
and get all the paper half dry.
The factory ran all day,
there was no lunch break,
they worked continuously for eight hours.
All the time was counted,
even when they ate.
Here we have to turn the ‘sarilho’,
and we have to attach the paper to the roll again
so as not to lose any time,
as quickly as possible, so that
as little paper as possible falls on the floor,
to save as much as possible.
We have to do that as quickly as we can,
turn that ‘sarilho’.
We saw it through with a rotating disc
and when it's cut through
it has to be done by hand, with a saw.
With a good sharp saw (without teeth)
so that it's not such hard work.
The sharper the saw,
the less it costs to cut the paper.
and then the girls hang it up above.
Then this cart goes to the lift,
the paper on the racks.
That's their job, hanging up the paper.
And that's quite heavy work too.
They have to lift the racks by hand,
as you may have already seen.
with a stick and a hook,
and then lift them up by hand.
That's pretty heavy.
And they're not that young anymore,
they're already in their fifties.
That's quite heavy work.
We put the paper on the table
and on the table we fold it
fold it
and hang it on the rack,
on the cross, and then on the rack.
And then we hoist the rack up.
We hoist the racks higher and higher,
until we have a gallery full.
A gallery has six racks.
Then we move on to the next gallery.
We go from gallery to gallery,
each gallery has six racks.
My name is Silvina Pinto,
I am 55 years old.
If necessary, I come here to help my sister
lift the racks upstairs.
This work is very hard,
very hard.
And that's how the paper is.
Then they make bales with this press here,
The girls do that too.
A bale weighs 50 kilos,
every bale weighs 50 kilos.
They put a wire on each side.
And then
they tighten the press with that iron,
they tighten the press.
And then they close the bale and take it off the press,
to put it on the pile.
In the past, the bales weighed 100 kilos,
then they became 50 kilos,
a long time ago already they became 50 kilos,
because people are getting weaker
and now they weigh about 25 kilos.
Their strength has diminished.
If necessary for an order
the boss comes with his delivery van
and we help with the loading,
with the bales on our heads.
Not in my case,
but the girls do that.
Tie them down, and off they go.
If it rains, we have to put a tarpaulin over them,
so that the paper doesn't get wet,
otherwise it goes like this, in the open air.
And it seems to me...
that the story has been told.